<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<blogs>
  <blog>
    <id>1685330146</id>
    <title>The Immaculate Conception Cathedra</title>
    <author>Mataas na Bayan, Boac, Marinduque</author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>As a dedication and gratefulness to the Ina of Biglang Awa. The canonical coronation of the miraculous object of veneration took place in Boac on May 10,  1958 to mark its 100th anniversary. It was attended by thousands of pilgrims from the nearby provinces in southern Luzon and Bicol. On the 11th day of the month of November, is her feast day falls on. Now, in the present days, the cathedral still remains as one of the landmark of the province of Marinduque. Some of the interiors have been preserved. And it is where the Moriones Festival is being celebrated. The people of the province still preserves and protect the cathedral. And the legend of the cathedral is still being passed on generations to not forgot to be grateful and to keep the history alive.</content>
    <restaurants>Kusina sa Plaza</restaurants>
    <events>Moriones Festival, </events>
    <activities>Boac Mayflower Festival Hermanidad 2023  During the</activities>
    <image>uploads/Boac.jpg</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685331036</id>
    <title>The Immaculate Conception Cathedral Parish</title>
    <author>Gasan, Marinduque</author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>Gasan is one of the municipalities that comprise the island province of Marinduque.  It is right next to  the municipality of Boac. My trip to Gasan was unforgettable because of this beautiful church again, located on top of a hill, overlooking the vast blue ocean (I don’t know if it’s West Philippine Sea or Pacific Ocean.)Going to the church is a bit of a challenge. You could go either climb the stairs or ride a vehicle all the way to the top.  Which way you choose, reaching the top is worth the climb.&#13;
Outside the church is a beautiful garden. On one portion was a spot that showcases several old church bells probably used by the church in the olden days.&#13;
A view deck was also made for the panoramic view of the town of Gasan, its beaches and a row of islands called by locals as “Tres Reyes”. Lucky for me during my visit because I was able to see too a beautiful scene of the sun setting.&#13;
</content>
    <restaurants>Goodchow Food Express.</restaurants>
    <events>Gasang-Gasang Festival</events>
    <activities>None</activities>
    <image>uploads/Gasan church pic.jpg</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685332166</id>
    <title>Holy Cross Parish - Sta. Cruz Marinduque</title>
    <author>Sta. Cruz, Marinduque </author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>The Sta. Cruz Church is the oldest in the province, constructed in 1760, with intricately-carved retablos and pulpit still intact today. Even with renovations done in recent years, most of this historic church’s interiors and furnishings are well-preserved.&#13;
Like other churches in the country, it stands majestically over all other structures in the community. According to the inscription on its main door, the church was constructed in 1760. This makes it the oldest standing structure in the province, even older than the Boac Church, which was constructed in 1792 by the Jesuit priests.&#13;
The church was not only built for worship; it was also designed to provide natives a refuge in times of calamities and attacks by Moro pirates. It did serve its purpose very well. When piracy was at its height, a deep moat was constructed parallel to the walls to make it doubly difficult to penetrate the church defenses. The tile roofing destroyed by a quake was eventually replaced with galvanized iron from Europe and it has effectively preserved the whole structure for posterity.</content>
    <restaurants>Kamayan sa palaisdaan</restaurants>
    <events>Ati-Atihan Festival</events>
    <activities>None</activities>
    <image>uploads/Marinduque-Sta.-Cruz-Church.png</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685332874</id>
    <title>Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary </title>
    <author> Boac, Marinduque</author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>Up next is a piece of greenery that occupies nearly 9,000 hectares of land, the Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary. It is home to several bird species such as the Zebra Dove, Serpent Eagle, Brahminy Kite, and Philippine Scops Owl. Adding to the lush green landscape are native trees such as Ipil, Narra, Yakal, and Molave.&#13;
&#13;
Inside the wildlife sanctuary are caves that serve as a habitat for rare species, like the cave-dwelling freshwater shrimp. Some wild animals inhabiting the protected land are the Philippine warty pig, the Philippine deer, the cloud rat, and the green racket tail. &#13;
&#13;
The Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary was declared as a protected land area in 2004 under Presidential Proclamation No. 696. Its forest watershed encompasses the municipalities of Boac, Gasan, Buenavista, Torrijos and Sta. Cruz. The Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary is a must-visit hiking, camping, and bird-watching spot for nature lovers and adventurous travelers.</content>
    <restaurants>Casa De Don Emilio</restaurants>
    <events>None</events>
    <activities> hiking, camping, and bird-watching spot for nature lovers and adventurous travelers.</activities>
    <image>uploads/top-10-marinduque-tourist-spots-beaches-islands-caves-nature-parks-3.avif</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685333383</id>
    <title>Bagumbungan Cave </title>
    <author>Sta. Cruz, Marinduque </author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>For those who like to experience spelunking in the Philippines, you can check out one of Marinduque’s subterranean wonders, the Bagumbungan Cave. It is often compared to Sumaguing Cave in Sagada because of its stalactites and stalagmites in impressive shapes and forms. Bagumbungan Cave is a great spelunking spot that features magnificent rock formations.  &#13;
The jump-off point is at the Santa Cruz town where the cave is located. At the cave’s entrance, there is a pathway leading down the waist-deep underground river basin. To get there, you have to pass through slippery surfaces and narrow passages. The path gets a bit more challenging as you slide down the muddy paths and squeeze yourself between huge rocks.&#13;
&#13;
Bagumbungan Cave is 1.9KM long and has a beginner-friendly trail, ideal for those who are new to spelunking. Some parts of the cave are off-limits for tourists. It remains largely unexplored, making it a wonderland for adventure seekers out there.</content>
    <restaurants>Ridian’s Food House</restaurants>
    <events>no events</events>
    <activities>Climbing and Hiking</activities>
    <image>uploads/top-10-marinduque-tourist-spots-beaches-islands-caves-nature-parks-7.avif</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685333709</id>
    <title> Mount Malindig</title>
    <author> Buenavista Marinduque</author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>Majestically standing on an elevation of 1,157 meters above sea level, Mount Malindig is a must-visit Buenavista Marinduque tourist spot and is considered the highest peak in the province. It is a stratovolcano situated at the island’s southern tip and west side of the Bondoc Peninsula on Luzon Island.&#13;
&#13;
Read our article about hiking in the Philippines&#13;
Because of its vast landscape and thriving ecosystem, Mount Malindig is comparable to Mt. Banahaw and Mt. Makiling in Quezon and Laguna provinces of Southern Luzon. At the base of Mount Malindig lies a therapeutic sulfuric spring called the Malbog Sulfur Spring. Many locals and tourists flock here to experience the healing powers of the spring.&#13;
&#13;
Mount Malindig is a hike-friendly destination for mountaineers. Based on the Pinoy Mountaineer rating system, it has a difficulty level of 4, which requires a minor climb. Having a trail classification level 1 and 2, Mount Malinig has a well-established trail with somewhat rugged and steep paths.</content>
    <restaurants>Konohauz</restaurants>
    <events>no events</events>
    <activities>Hiking and Camping</activities>
    <image>uploads/3_1600733635_d2b5c.png</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685334369</id>
    <title>Tres Reyes Islands</title>
    <author>Gasan, Marinduque</author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>Another postcard-worthy spot in Marinduque, the Treys Reyes Islands, is nestled off the coast of Gasan municipality. The jump-off point is at Gasan port where tour boats await passengers before heading to the neighboring Three Kings islets, namely Melchor, Gaspar, and Baltazar.&#13;
The largest among the three is Gaspar Island, a tranquil paradise with crystal clear waters and fine white sand. Next is Melchor Island, featuring rock formations covered in lush vegetation. Lastly, the Baltazar Island offers a lovely haven for those seeking a secluded spot to laze on the sand and lounge in beach cabanas.&#13;
&#13;
Among the must-see spots on Baltazar Island is a hilltop lighthouse, which was built during the American colonial period in 1910. Before capping off your island escapade, don’t forget to see the unique rock formations at Kulapnit Cave. Then, drop by the Kay Bungo Cave, a historical site where elongated skulls were found. </content>
    <restaurants>Curba Grill</restaurants>
    <events>no events</events>
    <activities>Island hopping</activities>
    <image>uploads/top-10-marinduque-tourist-spots-beaches-islands-caves-nature-parks-5.avif</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685335388</id>
    <title>Maniwaya Island</title>
    <author>Sta. Cruz, Marinduque </author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>Among all the famed destinations in Marinduque, Maniwaya Island should be on top of your bucket list. It is one of the several islands in Marinduque dotting Santa Cruz town that can rival famous white-sand beaches in the Philippines. Along the shoreline, you can find budget-friendly resorts and glamping cottages that resemble those in Bali, Indonesia.&#13;
Off the northern coast of the island is Palad Sandbar, a patch of white sand that unravels and seemingly invites you to dip into the surrounding crystal blue waters. The best time to visit the sandbar is in the morning, as the whole strip of white sand appears during low tide.&#13;
The stunning backdrop of the palm-fringed shores and turquoise-colored waters is perfect for taking Instagrammable selfies and group photos. To cap off your trip, don’t miss out on the chance to witness the best view of the sunset on Maniwaya Island.</content>
    <restaurants>Wawie's Beach Resort</restaurants>
    <events>no events</events>
    <activities>Swimming, Camping</activities>
    <image>uploads/mainpicmaniwaya.jpg</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685335715</id>
    <title>Poctoy White Beach </title>
    <author>Torrijos, Marinduque</author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>Among the well-known attractions in Marinduque is the Poctoy White Beach, a long stretch of fine white sand lined with palm trees in the coastal municipality of Torrijos. Surrounding the powdery beach are crystal clear waters that are ideal for swimming and kayaking. There are beachfront huts and cottages with chairs and tables, perfect for spending laidback afternoons on the beach.&#13;
&#13;
Underneath the crystalline waters is a sight to behold for scuba divers. The Poctoy Underwater Museum showcases giant Moryon monuments, which symbolize Marinduqueños iconic Moriones festival that happens every Holy Week.&#13;
&#13;
Aside from being one of the idyllic beaches in Marinduque, Poctoy White Beach remains to be among the emerging Torrijos Marinduque tourist spots. It attracts many local and international travelers annually because of its pristine shores and panoramic sunset views glowing over the horizon.</content>
    <restaurants>Club Cagpo</restaurants>
    <events>no events</events>
    <activities>Swimming, Camping</activities>
    <image>uploads/Poctoy Torrijos White Beach Marinduque.jpg</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685336167</id>
    <title>Paadjao falls </title>
    <author>Mogpog, Marindque</author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>While Marinduque is famous for its scenic beaches, there is one enchanting waterfall that stands out from the rest of the Mogpog Marinduque tourist spots, the Paadjao Falls. Situated in Mogpog municipality, the Paadjao Falls is accessible via a 10-minute trek from the highway, which is only 5.5KM away. &#13;
The hidden cascade gently flows from a 15-feet tall rocky cliff down to a 6-feet deep basin with cold and jade-green waters. It majestically nestles underneath the cool shade of verdant greenery and tall trees, making you feel a lot closer to nature. Surrounding the falls are huge and edgy rocks, so be extra careful when crossing the river and falls.&#13;
&#13;
Paadjao Falls is connected to the Mogpog River downstream. It is also an ideal picnic spot where guests can put up tents for camping. Aside from Paadjao Falls, there are other underrated waterfalls in Marinduque such as Norada Falls, Kawa Kawa Falls, and Bulusukan Falls.</content>
    <restaurants>Kalamigans</restaurants>
    <events>no events</events>
    <activities>Swimming</activities>
    <image>uploads/Marinduque-Paadjao-Falls.jpg</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685336574</id>
    <title>Mongpong Island</title>
    <author>Sta. Cruz, Marinduque </author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>Off the northeastern coast of Marinduque is Mongpong Island, a charming islet with striking rock formations and a pristine white-sand beach. It has clear blue waters where you can see through colorful reef fishes underwater.&#13;
&#13;
Upon arrival on the island, the Ungab Rock Formation is the first thing that will pique your interest. The huge colossal rock sits on the island’s turquoise waters and white sand. Carved out of the base rock is a triangular hole that forms a land bridge connecting you to the other side of the beach.  &#13;
&#13;
The giant boulder is a sight to behold and a perfect backdrop for your selfies and group photos. Plus, the water underneath the rock arch is shallow, making it a safe spot to swim for kids. The white sand is also a mixture of smooth pebbles and coral fragments.</content>
    <restaurants>El Marinduqueños Island Resort</restaurants>
    <events>no events</events>
    <activities>Swimming, Camping</activities>
    <image>uploads/ungabmain.jpg</image>
  </blog>
  <blog>
    <id>1685336837</id>
    <title>Malbog Sulfur Spring</title>
    <author>Buenavista, Marinduque</author>
    <date>May/29/2023</date>
    <content>Malbog Sulfur Spring is a natural hot spring at the foot of a volcano known as Mount Malindig. It is a stratovolcano in the Buenavista town with an elevation of 1,157 meters above sea level.&#13;
Malbog Sulfur Spring nestles within lush greenery surrounded by verdant flora and fauna. Its warm and bluish-white sulfuric water is believed to have therapeutic and healing benefits. The spring has two swimming pools, and both have medicinal properties that can cure skin diseases. &#13;
&#13;
The stream directly comes from the mountain and goes down into a spring pool where tourists can have a rejuvenating dip. Its water is safe to drink and is even believed to cure acute and chronic cases of skin ailments. Some tourists even bring bottles of sulfuric water on their way home.</content>
    <restaurants>Curba grill</restaurants>
    <events>no events</events>
    <activities>swimming</activities>
    <image>uploads/Becoming Filipino Kulas_Malbog Sulfuric Hotspring Buenavista Marinduque (17).jpg</image>
  </blog>
</blogs>
